<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preach'd to the Protestants of Ireland in the city of London at St. Helens, Octob. 23, 1690 being the day appointed by act of Parliament in Ireland for an anniversary thanksgiving for the deliverence of the Protestants of that kingdom from the bloody massacre begun by the Irish papists on the 23d of October, 1641 / by Richard, Lord Bishop of Killala.</title>
            <author>Tenison, Richard, 1640?-1705.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1691</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 60 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 16 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A64348</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T684</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R9854</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13768601</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13768601</idno>
            <idno type="VID">101735</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A64348)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 101735)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 852:37)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preach'd to the Protestants of Ireland in the city of London at St. Helens, Octob. 23, 1690 being the day appointed by act of Parliament in Ireland for an anniversary thanksgiving for the deliverence of the Protestants of that kingdom from the bloody massacre begun by the Irish papists on the 23d of October, 1641 / by Richard, Lord Bishop of Killala.</title>
                  <author>Tenison, Richard, 1640?-1705.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 27, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Robert Clavel ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1691.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"Printed at the earnest request of many of the gentry of Ireland."</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Chronicles, 2nd, XXVII, 9 --  Sermons.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <pb facs="tcp:101735:1"/>
            <p>Imprimatur,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>C. Alſton,</hi> R. P. D. <hi>Henrico,</hi> Epiſc. <hi>Lond.</hi> à Sacris.</signed> 
               <date>Novemb. 4. 1690.</date>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:101735:1"/>
            <p>A SERMON Preach'd to the Proteſtants OF IRELAND IN THE CITY of <hi>LONDON,</hi> At St. <hi>Helens, Octob.</hi> 23. 1690.</p>
            <p>BEING The Day Appointed by Act of Parliament in <hi>IRELAND</hi> FOR AN Anniverſary Thankſgiving For the Deliverance of the Proteſtants of that King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, from the Bloody Maſſacre begun by the <hi>Iriſh Papiſts</hi> on the 23d. of <hi>October,</hi> 1641.</p>
            <p>By <hi>RICHARD,</hi> Lord Biſhop of <hi>Killala.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Printed at the Earneſt Requeſt of many of the Gentry of</hi> Ireland.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>Robert Clavel,</hi> at the <hi>Peacock</hi> in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-yard. 1691.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:101735:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:101735:2"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>2 CHRON. xxviii. 9.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Behold, becauſe the Lord God of your Fathers was wroth with <hi>Judah,</hi> he hath delivered them into your hands: and ye have ſlain them in a rage that reacheth up to Heaven.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>WHEN the Royal Tribe of <hi>Judah</hi> did highly offend and diſpleaſe Almighty God; when the many ſignal Mercies and Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours which he had beſtowed upon them, could not oblige them to obey his Laws, and keep his Commandments, he afflicts them with many, and great Judgments, to ſee if that could reduce them to Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence. He had long waited for their Converſion; and ſent his Prophets early and late to admoniſh and fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warn them of their danger: He courted and allur'd them with Temporal Bleſſings; and promiſed them a perpetual continuance of his Favour. But when all theſe Methods proved ineffectual, and nothing could work upon them; he then ſhowr'd down the Vials of his Wrath and Indigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Beſide their great and deſerved Sufferings mentioned in other places, this Chapter tells you, that God deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them into the Hands of a Forreign Prince, who ſmote them, and carried a vaſt Multitude of them Priſoners to <hi>Damaſcus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This was a very great and a heavy Puniſhment, to be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced from their plentiful Habitations; to live in Exile and Bondage; poor, and unpitied; groaning with the weight of their uneaſie Chains; and languiſhing in dark and loath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome Dungeons: But when even this could have no influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:101735:3"/>upon them, he afflicts them with a Domeſtick and Inteſtine War: Their own Brethren roſe up againſt them, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe </seg>6</label> and cruelly ſlaughter'd a Hundred and twenty Thouſand in one day, who were all Valiant Men. A ſad and diſmal ſight, to ſee ſo many weltring in their blood! The Great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt and moſt Honourable Courtiers were then alſo kill'd; and Two Hundred Thouſand Women and Children were led Captives to <hi>Samaria.</hi> Thus dangerous and fatal is it to provoke and incenſe the Lord.</p>
            <p>This Puniſhment did far exceed the other: The Wounds which we receive from a Friend's Sword, are moſt pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and tormenting.<note place="margin">Pſal. 55.13.</note> 
               <hi>David</hi> ſays, <hi>Had it been an Enemy, I could have born it; but it was thou mine equal and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Laws of God and Nature are more violated by Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſtick Feuds and Treaſons, than by Forreign Quarrels and Invaſions: And none more rigid and unmerciful than thoſe of our own Houſe and Country. This was evidently ſeen in the Cruelties of the Men of <hi>Iſrael;</hi> who not only kill'd ſuch a prodigious number of their Brethren, and took much Spoil from them, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe </seg>15</label> but brought away many Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands of them and their Children naked and barefoot, fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and wounded, to be their Bondmen and Vaſſals: And ſo mercileſs and ſevere were they in all reſpects, that a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet is ſent to reprove and rebuke them; who, with un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daunted Courage ſtands at the head of their bloody Troops, and cries out, <hi>Behold, becauſe the Lord God of your Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers was wroth with</hi> Judah, <hi>he hath delivered them into your hands; and ye have ſlain them in a rage that reacheth up to Heaven:</hi> In which you may obſerve,
<list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Firſt,</hi> 
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="I"/> God's delivering the men of <hi>Judah</hi> into the hands of the men of <hi>Iſrael.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Secondly,</hi> 
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="II"/> The Reaſon of it: becauſe he was wroth with them.</item>
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:101735:3"/>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Thirdly,</hi> 
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="III"/> The Prophet's Reproof of the Cruelty of the Men of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> for ſlaying their Brethren with a Rage that reached up to Heaven.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>First,</hi> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> God's delivering the Men of <hi>Judah</hi> into the hands of the Men of <hi>Iſrael.</hi> The whole Scripture doth abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly declare how merciful and gracious God is, how ſlow to anger, and how unwilling to puniſh: But when his Mercies are ſlighted, his Favours rejected, and all his Invitations and Threatnings are vilified and contemned, he then exerts his Power, his Veracity and Juſtice, and makes himſelf terrible to the Children of Men, by throwing down his Judgments upon them.</p>
            <p>Here you ſee, the Men of <hi>Judah</hi> were given up: That Tribe, which was to be eternally famous by our Saviour's Birth, that very Tribe did he ſuffer to be thus ſeverely puniſhed. Whence, 'tis evident, that God exempts none, but whoſoever ſins ſhall be puniſhed. That Nation, or Family that offends God, and runs into open Hoſtility a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him, ſhall ſuffer. If he ſpared not <hi>Judah,</hi> none muſt hope for Pardon and Immunity. And if you ſearch the Divine Annals, you'll find, that when-ever they wallowed in Sin, and ſlept in ſecurity, then did God rouze them with the noiſe of War, and brought Devaſtations and Deſolati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons upon them: He ſurrounded them with Enemies on every ſide, and did by them laſh them in, when they ran into Rebellion againſt him.</p>
            <p>And if he uſed them thus; if he ſpared not the Natural Branches, take heed leſt he ſpare not you; for thus will he deal with all who will not be reformed: He will with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw his Protection, and leave them to themſelves, and let their Enemies invade their Houſes, and ruine their Country; of which, the many Conqueſts in <hi>Judea,</hi> and the Diſperſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of their Tribes over all the Earth, is a remarkable and dreadful Example.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:101735:4"/>
            <p> The <hi>Pſalmist</hi> tells us,<note place="margin">Pſal. 34 7.</note> 
               <hi>The Angel of the Lord encampeth round about them that fear him, and delivereth them:</hi> But they who will not fear him, ſhall have no ſuch mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration and attendance: Their Guardian-Angels remove, as they did from the Temple, before <hi>Titus</hi> ſack'd <hi>Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem;</hi> when (as <hi>Joſephus</hi> and <hi>Euſebius</hi> tell us) a Voice was heard, <hi>Let us depart hence;</hi> and they were left to themſelves, and lay open to the Aſſaults of their Enemies, and were then ſoon ruin'd and ſcatter'd up and down the World, near two Millions of them being deſtroyed in ſour Years; Eleven Hundred Thouſand fell in the City, Ninety Seven Thouſand were taken Priſoners, and Thirty of them were ſold for a Peny. Thus lamentable and dreadful is the Condition of that People who are forſaken of the Lord, who are left void and deſtitute of his Protection: <hi>I will forſake them and hide my face from them, and many evils and trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles ſhall befal them, ſo that they will ſay in that day, Are not theſe evils come upon us becauſe our God is not amongst us?</hi> Deut. 31.17.</p>
            <p>Beware then of driving God away from you; where he withdraws and abſents himſelf, no good thing can conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue: While we are his People, he will be our God, but no longer. If we renounce our Allegiance to a Mortal Prince, he'll ſoon with-hold his Favours from us, and Correct us according to the nature of our Crimes: And ſhall we ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect to go free, when we violate our Loyalty and Homage to Almighty God? That were inconſiſtent with his Juſtice; for being a juſt Judge, he muſt Puniſh and give Sentence, <hi>Amos</hi> 3.2. And he declares his Reſolutions of puniſhing them this way, Lev. 26.17. <hi>Ye ſhall be ſlain before your enemies; they that hate you ſhall reign over you, and ye ſhall flee when none purſue.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Many other ſuch grievous Comminations are in his Word, which were exactly fulfill'd; God making them a Prey to their Enemies, and ſcattering them up and down
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:101735:4"/>the Earth. And ſtill you may obſerve, the Scripture ſays, God gave them up: God cauſed them to be ſmitten: As in the Text you are told, <hi>God delivered</hi> Judah <hi>into the hands of the</hi> Iſraelites; which teacheth us two things:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>First,</hi> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> That without God's permiſſion, our Enemies can have no power over us. 'Tis when he forſakes, when he delivers us up, that our Enemies overcome us; till he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, they cannot move: till by ſin we forfeit our Right to his Protection, we need not fear; which ſhews us our comfort and ſecurity, and may arm us againſt diſſidence and diſtruſt; for though they long to deſtroy us, though they gnaſh at us with their Teeth, and thirſt after our Blood, they cannot hurt us, till God permit them. He reſtrains them by his power, and keeps us under the hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low of his hand.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> It ſhews us, that whatever Judgments happen to a People, God ſends, or permits them:<note place="margin">Iſa. 45.7. <hi>Grot. Piſc.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>'Tis he that makes peace, and creates our evil;</hi> our Calamities of War, Peſtilence, or Famine, as Interpreters render it. And the <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> tells us,<note place="margin">Pſal. 46.8.</note> 
               <hi>'Tis he that makes deſolations in the earth.</hi> And what Judgments fall upon us, come from him, as a juſt Retribution of our Wickedneſs. He makes uſe of ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Rods to Correct us; now Foreign Invaſions, then Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſtick Rebellions; he ſuffers our Neighbours to riſe up, and deſtroy us; and owns himſelf the Avenger of Iniquity,<note place="margin">Rom. 12.19.</note> nor will he loſe the Glory of the greateſt Executions; <hi>for Vengeance is his, and he will repay it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Such Acts are the outward ſigns and demonſtrations of his Juſtice and Omniſcience; and our ſighs and groans in Adverſity contribute to his Honour, as well as our Praiſes and Thankſgivings in Proſperity. The ſhrieks and cries of the Damned in Hell bring Glory to him, as well as the Anthems and Hallelujahs of the Saints in Heaven:<note place="margin">Gen. 18.25.</note> 
               <hi>for ſhall not the Judge of all the earth do right?</hi> His Juſtice ſhould be conſpicuous to all the World, and the moſt punitive effects
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:101735:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>thereof, are for his Honour, and tend to our benefit and advantage. They make us acknowledge his Power, and fear his Wrath; and own, with the <hi>Pſalmiſt, that there is a God which judgeth in the earth, Pſal.</hi> 58.11. They make us turn to him with Sorrow and Repentance, with Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation and Amendment:<note place="margin">Iſa. 26.9.</note> 
               <hi>And when his Judgments are in the earth, we will learn Righteouſneſs. Nunquam Dei memine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rint, niſi dum in malis fuerint,</hi> ſays <hi>Lactantius.</hi> We ſeldom remember God as we ought, but when his hand lies heavy upon us, and preſſes us down ſore; ſo that for the vindicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of his own Honour, and for our good, 'tis neceſſary we ſhould be puniſh'd and chaſtis'd.</p>
            <p>'Tis true, all his Corrections are not out of Anger, ſome proceed from his Love, and are ſent as Antidotes to prevent ſin, and improve our Graces; to draw us nearer to him, and increaſe our dependance upon him; to know him and our ſelves better; to diſcern our Frailties and Weakneſs, to wean our hearts from this vain and tranſitory World, to give us a clear ſight and ſence of our Offences; to make us Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidents of Courage and Conſtancy unto others, and to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt his own Glory in our Deliverance.</p>
            <p>And ſuch, I hope, are thoſe which we now ſuffer: And therefore beware how you cenſure thoſe who groan under the ſharpeſt Tryals, and moſt grievous Calamities; for in all Ages of the World, the holieſt Perſons have gone through much Tribulation to the Kingdom of Heaven. Not to mention the Sufferings of the Patriarchs and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, do but ſee what happened to the Diſciples and Fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers of the Holy Jeſus. Was not St. <hi>Matthew</hi> Martyr'd in <hi>Aethiopia,</hi> St. <hi>Mark</hi> burnt, St. <hi>Luke</hi> hanged, and St. <hi>John</hi> thrown into a Cauldron of Oyl? Was not St. <hi>Peter</hi> crucified, and St. <hi>Paul</hi> beheaded? And were not the reſt put to various and cruel Deaths? And it would grate your Ears, and make your Hearts tremble to hear the Tortures of Chriſtians in the Ten Perſecutions. <hi>They ſlew them in
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:101735:5"/>a rage that reached up to Heaven. Severus</hi> ordered that none of them ſhould be left alive in all his Territories: And <hi>Nicephorus</hi> tells us, we may as well count the Grains of Sand, as the Names of all that were Martyred under the Inhumane <hi>Decius:</hi> And in all Ages ſince, the beſt Chriſtians have undergone great Tryals and Afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</p>
            <p>So that you muſt be very cautious how you judge of the Sufferings of Kingdoms, of Families, and Individual Perſons: You muſt not think their Calamities are always ſent for the Puniſhment of ſome grievous ſin; and that the greateſt Sufferers are the greateſt Offenders: God ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving many other Ends and Reaſons for viſiting us with Afflictions; and they are Marks and Tokens of his Love, his Fatherly Care and Protection, and of our Filiation and Adoption, as well as of his Wrath and Diſpleaſure:<note place="margin">Heb. 12.6.</note> 
               <hi>For whom the Lord loveth, he chaſteneth; and ſcourgeth every Son whom he receiveth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But we muſt alſo know, that Judgments do often pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed from his Wrath, and are the juſt Puniſhments of ſin: and therefore in publick or private Calamities, we ſhould ſearch and examine our own Hearts, and ſee, with <hi>Job,</hi> why God contendeth with us; and repent and bewail our ſins, and reſolve upon uniform Obedience for the future: We ſhould give Glory to God, and take ſhame and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion of face to our ſelves, and own our Sufferings to be far leſs then we deſerve, and ſay,<note place="margin">Pſal. 145.17.</note> 
               <hi>The Lord is righteous in all his ways, and holy in all his works.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And let us never imagine they fall upon us by meer Accident,<note place="margin">Job 5.6.</note> or Chance: <hi>For affliction ariſeth not out of the duſt, nor trouble out of the mire.</hi> We cannot periſh but by his knowledge, conſent, or permiſſion: His Judgments are the juſt and uſual effects and conſequents of our ſin, and are generally ſent either to puniſh us for it, or to
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:101735:6"/>keep us from committing it: And therefore in National or particular Judgments, let us ſtill look at that great Hand from whence they come, and humble our ſelves under it, and be dumb becauſe God does it. The Text tells you, He delivered <hi>Judah</hi> into the Hands of their Enemies: If he had not done ſo, they could not have deſtroy'd them: And it alſo gives you the Reaſon of it, which is the <hi>ſecond thing</hi> to be conſidered.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly, He was wroth with them:</hi> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Becauſe he was angry with them, he delivered them to their Tormen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors. The <hi>Iſraelites</hi> could not arrogate this Victory to themſelves: It was not their Innocency, or their Merit which obtained it, for they were ſinners as well as the men of <hi>Judah,</hi> as the Prophet tells them in the next Verſe; <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe </seg>6</label> but they were the ſins of the men of <hi>Judah</hi> which occaſioned it; <hi>becauſe they had forſaken the Lord God of their Fathers,</hi> Pekah <hi>ſlew in one day an hundred and twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty thouſand.</hi> It was their ſin of forſaking God which gave their Enemies that mighty Conqueſt and Succeſs: 'Twas that which enabled them to ſubdue ſo many ſtout men at one time.</p>
            <p>Whence obſerve, That neither Courage nor Conduct, Strength nor Magnanimity, can withſtand the Power and Will of God; there is no reſiſting his Almighty Arm, when he is provoked by our ſins. 'Tis ſaid, <hi>When the Lion roars, all the Beasts of the Foreſt tremble:</hi> And well may poor Mortals quake when God is angry. A due conſideration of his Power and our own Guilt, may fill the ſtouteſt Heart with Dread and Terror.<note place="margin">Pſal. 119.120.</note> 
               <hi>David,</hi> though a man of invincible Courage, cries out, <hi>My fleſh trembleth for fear of thee; and I am afraid of thy Judgments.</hi> He knew God could afflict him with Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual, Temporal, and Eternal Judgments; the apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of which did ſo terrifie him, that he could neither
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:101735:6"/>ſleep nor ſpeak. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 77.4. <hi>Thou keepeſt me waking, and I am aſtoniſhed; I am ſo troubled that I cannot ſpeak.</hi> And he gives the Reaſon of this in the next Verſe; <hi>I have conſider'd the days of Old, the years of ancient times:</hi> or the <hi>eternal years,</hi> as the <hi>Septuagint</hi> renders it.</p>
            <p>'Tis a dangerous thing to provoke a God who is armed and inveſted with ſuch Power; it is not ſafe to ſtir up his Anger and Wrath: For as <hi>David</hi> tells you,<note place="margin">Pſal. 90.11.</note> 
               <hi>Who know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the power of thine anger? Even according to thy fear, ſo is thy wrath.</hi> And the Epithets, <hi>Hot, Great, Fierce Burning,</hi> and <hi>Smoaking,</hi> are generally added to the Anger of God in Scripture, to ſhew the great danger of exci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting his wrath, and the difficulty of reſiſting it, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fending our ſelves againſt the fatal conſequences of it, when 'tis once kindled: <hi>It being,</hi> as the Apoſtle ſays,<note place="margin">Heb. 10.31.</note> 
               <hi>a fearful thing to fall into the hands of the living God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What vaſt Armies have been defeated, what flouriſhing Cities have been conſumed, what Noble Countries have been laid waſte in his Anger, you may at large ſee in Scripture. All the Elements are at his Command, and can deſtroy us when he pleaſes. The Earth, the Sea, and even Hell it ſelf have opened their voracious mouths, and ſwallowed down numbers in his wrath. Angels have come from Heaven, and ſlain whole Armies at a time. If one of thoſe powerful Spirits could ſlay 185000 in a Night, (as one did in the Army of <hi>Sennacherib</hi>) what can the whole Hoaſt of Heaven do, when God is enraged againſt us?</p>
            <p>Obſerve therefore the Advice of <hi>Moſes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Deut. 6.13.</note> 
               <hi>and fear the Lord thy God, and ſerve him; lest the anger of the Lord thy God be kindled against thee, and deſtroy thee from off the face of the earth.</hi> How ſoon did he make it open, and ſwallow down <hi>Corah</hi> and his Confederates? And did he not rain down Fire and Brimſtone from Heaven upon
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:101735:7"/>
               <hi>Sodom</hi> and <hi>Gomorrha?</hi> Which with many other ſudden Judgments in Holy Writ, may terrifie us from incurring his Indignation. Remember alſo what he did to his own People of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> whom he brought through the Red Sea, and fed with Manna in the Wilderneſs; and dread the like Executions of his Vengeance, and ſeriouſly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, <hi>That except ye repent, ye ſhall all likewiſe pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Compare your ſins with theirs, and you will ſoon find that you have reaſon to fear as great, and as heavy ſtrokes; for ſin was never more openly committed, and all ſorts of Impiety did never more abound, than they have done of late years in theſe Nations. The Records of God's former Puniſhments have had little Operation upon theſe Kingdoms. And we, alas! who are now met together, may with ſhame and ſorrow confeſs, that the dreadful Judgment, which we this day commemorate, did not Reform us: And therefore God hath juſtly puniſhed us again, in delivering us into the hands of our Enemies; who, but for the Terror of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Arms, would, in all probability, have ſlain us, as the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> did the men of <hi>Judah,</hi> with a rage that would have reached up to Heaven: Which is the <hi>Third</hi> thing in the Text to be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cours'd on.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Their cruel uſage of the men of <hi>Judah,</hi> in ſlaying them with a rage that reached up to Heaven.</p>
            <p>When once God gives up a People to be puniſh'd, the Devil inſtigates the Executioners to do it with all poſſible Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice and Inveteracy. They gratifie their revengeful Appetite at ſuch times; their Ambition and Rigour increaſe with their Power: They throw off all ſentiments of Humanity, and are pleaſed with thoſe Tragical Spectacles, which Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſhrinks at, and abhors. Thus did <hi>Adonibezek</hi> cut off the Thumbs and great Toes of ſeventy Kings, and made
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:101735:7"/>then feed at his feet, and eat the crumbs which fell from his Table. <hi>Seſoſtris,</hi> King of <hi>Egypt,</hi> was of the ſame cruel Temper: He delighted to hear the Kings whom he had conquered, groan as they drew his Chariot. And did not <hi>Lyſimachus</hi> laugh to ſee <hi>Teleſphorus,</hi> whoſe Ears and Noſe, and Lips he had cut off, bemoan himſelf in his tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menting Cage? in which he barbarouſly expos'd him to be ſeen, as ſome ſtrange Creature. The like might I tell you of <hi>Cyrus</hi> and <hi>Cambyſes,</hi> of <hi>Nero</hi> and <hi>Caligula,</hi> of <hi>Domitian</hi> and <hi>Decius:</hi> But how remarkably did God puniſh theſe, and many other cruel Men? Did not <hi>Cambyſes,</hi> who mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered his Wife and his Brother, and ſlaughtered his Nobi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity for nothing; and cut off all the <hi>Syrians</hi> Noſes, fall by his own Sword, and his mercileſs Army eat one another in <hi>Aethiopia?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As they did to others, ſo did God requite them: He abhors their Tyranny, and inſatiable thirſt after Blood: And his permitting them to puniſh others, will not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quit their Spight and Malice, their Rancour and Spleen, their Rage and Cruelty in doing of it. Theſe are ſins which proceed from their own corrupt Nature, their per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe Will and free Choice, and not from any inevitable Neceſſity, or irreſiſtible Force impoſed upon them by Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God. <hi>He tempteth not any man to ſin,</hi>
               <note place="margin">James 1.13:</note> ſaith St. <hi>James.</hi> He being Holy, Juſt, and Perfect, cannot ſeduce man to that which is ſinful, and concur in the evil of his Actions. He withdraws his Grace, which ſoftens and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrains the Heart; and for want thereof, the Heart is har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dened, as the Earth is by the Sun, when its ſoftning moi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture is exhaled and drawn up by it: And leaving Man to himſelf thus hardned, he is then drawn away with his own Luſts, and chooſes, wills, and commits ſin, for which he is juſtly accountable. And ſuch mens malicious and revengeful Acts are highly offenſive and diſpleaſing unto
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:101735:8"/>God, for which he does often moſt ſeverely puniſh them. They are contrary to his Nature,<note place="margin">Lam. 3.33.</note> 
               <hi>who doth not afflict wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly, nor grieve the Children of men.</hi> He never ſtrikes but when he is forc'd; and therefore all delight in Cruelty muſt be moſt odious unto him.</p>
            <p>If an Executioner, inſtead of ſtriking off a man's Head, ſhould cut and mangle all his Body, and put him to much greater pain and torture than the Judge decreed, he is juſtly blam'd and puniſh'd. Here the juſt Judge of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven is angry with the bloody <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> for their ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere uſage of poor <hi>Judah,</hi> and ſends his Prophet to acquaint them with his Reſentments of their Barbarity, who un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dauntedly tells them of their ſin, and denounces the fierce wrath of the Lord againſt them. He did not fear what they could do unto him, neither muſt we dread any in publiſhing the Commands of God: We muſt cry aloud, and ſpare not, and imitate this zealous Prophet, in repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the Tyranny and Oppreſſion of bloody Men. He did not leſſen their Outrages, but upbraids them for ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding their Commiſſion, in ſlaying them with a Rage that reached up to Heaven. <hi>Ad Coelos pertigit, inde in ſe vindictam excitans.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Maſ.</note> Their great and unreaſonable Rage which they executed with ſo much ſeverity and delight, cry'd loud in Heaven, and made God puniſh them after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward. They ſhould not have been ſo ſevere to their own Brethren, nor took ſuch pleaſure and ſatisfaction in their Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment. God in Judgment remembers Mercy; and though he would humble his own People, and bring them low, he would not have them quite deſtroy'd.</p>
            <p>But ſo fierce and outragious are the Enemies of his Children, that inſtead of going, they run to deſtroy them; they thirſt after their Blood, and, like the Horſe-leech, burſt ere they are ſatisfied. No leſs than an Ocean of Blood could ſale the greedy Appetite of theſe Devourers;
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:101735:8"/>a hundred and twenty Thouſand Victims muſt be Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fic'd to their Malice.</p>
            <p>By which you ſee what a heavy Judgment it is to fall into the hands of inveterate Adverſaries. Well did <hi>David</hi> chooſe, when he ſinned in Numbring the People, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive his Puniſhment from God's own hand: <hi>For,</hi> as <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon</hi> tells you, <hi>the tender mercies of the wicked are cruel.</hi> Nothing but the height of Rage and Fury can be expected from them.</p>
            <p>Of this all Ages have given us many and ſad Examples: but none more than that in which this monſtrous and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parallel'd Cruelty was acted, which we this day are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded by the Law of our Nation to commemorate. For when God was wroth with us for our ſins, he ſuffered the <hi>Iriſh Papiſts</hi> to riſe up againſt us, and ſlay many Thouſands in a Rage that reached up to Heaven. Which horrid Fact, ſeeing they are grown ſo impudent and au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dacious to deny, and in their Pamphlets pretend there was only a little Commotion, and but ſome few kill'd; and that the Proteſtants were the firſt Aggreſſors: I ſhall (as I have been deſired) to undeceive you that are ſtrangers, and for the juſt Vindication of the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> take the uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Liberty allow'd to Preachers on theſe Occaſions, and ſhew you how their Rebellion began, who chiefly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triv'd it, and what cruel Actions they committed; by which you will ſoon perceive that they imitated theſe men in my Text, and ſlew their Brethren in a Rage that reached up to Heaven.</p>
            <p>The unhappy Natives of that Country having lived long in a blind Obedience and Vaſſalage to the Church of <hi>Rome;</hi> and believing the Pope Infallible, would not doubt the truth of what his <hi>Janizaries,</hi> the Jeſuits, did ſuggeſt unto them. Whatever any of their Clergy affirms Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, did then, and does ſtill paſs among the Vulgar for
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:101735:9"/>Catholick Doctrine; and no Oracle more unqueſtionable than their Aſſertions. <hi>Sic credit Eccleſia</hi> weighs down the Balance of Religion and Loyalty, let the Doctrine be never ſo contrary to the Laws of God and Nature.</p>
            <p>Being thus ignorant and credulous, and wholly devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to follow the Advice of their Clergy, they ran into Rebellion in the Year 1641. being inſtigated thereunto by their Church-men, who having plotted the Miſchief abroad, came over in Shoals the Year before, as was well known to Men of Wiſdom and Obſervation then living, and very apparent from the Intelligence King <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt then had from his Ambaſſadors in <hi>Spain,</hi> and other Countries; of which he gave timely Notice to his Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtices.</p>
            <p>Theſe grand Incendiaries diſperſing themſelves through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the Kingdom, and removing the Native Clergy of the <hi>Pale</hi> into remoter Parts of the Land, and placing men out of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lſter</hi> and <hi>Connaught,</hi> of more fierce and bloody Principles there, they blew up the Trumpet every where to riſe in Arms; branding us and our Religion with the blackeſt Calumnies, and moſt falſely telling the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, they were a Free Nation, and had no dependance up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>England,</hi> and ſhould therefore ſtrive to recover their Ancient Rights, and be no longer Subject to an Heretical Prince. I ſay, moſt falſely did they ſuggeſt, that <hi>Ireland</hi> was a Free Nation, when they cannot but own that it was Conquer'd ſome hundreds of Years ſince. In which caſe <hi>Grotius</hi> tells us,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>De jure be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> lib. 3. c. 6.</note> 
               <hi>Jure Gentium non tantum is qui ex ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtâ causâ bellum gerit, ſed &amp; quivis in bello ſolenni, &amp; ſine fine, modoque Dominus fit eorum quoe ex Hoſte eripit.</hi> Not only he that wages War in a Juſt Cauſe, but every Man in a Solemn War, is Lord and owner of what he takes from the Enemy. <hi>Xenophon</hi> calls it an Everlaſting Law with all Men. And <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> ſays, The Law of
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:101735:9"/>Nations, as by an Univerſal Agreement, had ordained, That the Conqueror ſhould enjoy what he Conquers; it being a general Rule, <hi>Quoe ex Hoſtibus capiuntur, Jure Gentium, ſtatim capientium fiunt.</hi> Whatever is taken from the Enemy, is, by the Law of Nations, his who takes it.</p>
            <p>If ſo, then certainly <hi>Ireland</hi> belongs to the Crown of <hi>England.</hi> For, not to inſiſt upon King <hi>Arthur</hi>'s Claim, when he ſummoned their Petit Princes to appear before him here, and own their Subjection to him.<note place="margin">Cambden.</note> Or upon King <hi>Edgar</hi>'s Conqueſt, who ſubdued <hi>Dublin,</hi> and the greateſt part of the Kingdom, and made them acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge his Soveraignty over them.<note place="margin">Giral. Cambr.</note> We all know that King <hi>Henry</hi> the Second reduc'd them to Obedience above Five Hundred Years ago; and Charters of Submiſſion to him were voluntarily ſigned and deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the ſeven Kings of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try,<note place="margin">They ſubmitted to <hi>Henry</hi> the Second, to King <hi>John,</hi> to <hi>Richard</hi> the Second, and to <hi>Henry</hi> the Eight, and their Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſions were ſworn to, ſigned, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corded; yet did they ſtill Rebel as ſoon as they had Opportunity. And though <hi>Oneal</hi> did in his Letters ſtyle <hi>Richard</hi> the Second his King, and perpetual Lord of <hi>Ireland,</hi> and in the Inſtrument of his Submiſſion uſed theſe words; <hi>Ego Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lanus Oneal, tam pro meipſo, quam pro filiis meis, &amp; tota Natione mea, &amp; pro omnibus ſubditis meis, devenio Ligeus ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo veſter,</hi> &amp;c. Yet did he run into Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion again, and committed great ſlaughters. By which they in thoſe days, and their Poſterity ſince, have verified the Prophecy which <hi>Giral. Cambr.</hi> men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, That after the firſt Invaſion of the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> they ſhould ſpend many Ages in frequent Conflicts, Battels, and Murders, and that almoſt all the <hi>Engliſh</hi> ſhould be driven out of <hi>Ireland,</hi> &amp;c.</note> and tranſmitted to <hi>Rome,</hi> which were confirmed by a Bull from Pope <hi>Adrian,</hi> and by the delivery of a Ring, in token of his Inveſtiture; to which both Clergy and Laity did conſent, and ſware Homage and Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alty to him in a Publick Convention at<note n="*" place="margin">Mat. Paris. Giral. Cambr.</note> 
               <hi>Liſmore,</hi> where the Laws of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> were alſo thankfully received, and they all ſworn to obſerve them: and afterward he gave it to his Son <hi>John,</hi> and the Pope confirmed it. And in the Synod at <hi>Caſhell,</hi> they did un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>animouſly, before <hi>Chriſtianus,</hi> Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſident thereof, acknowledge the King's Ancient Right to <hi>Ireland;</hi> and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyn'd all to be ſubject unto him. And there, and at ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:101735:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>General Synod held at <hi>Armagh,</hi> they order'd and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creed, That the Church of <hi>Ireland</hi> ſhould obſerve all Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Offices that the Church of <hi>England</hi> did; and there alſo was the King's lawful Right again confeſs'd, and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted unto: and for Four hundred years after it was cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the King's Land of <hi>Ireland;</hi> and, by many Acts of Parliament,<note place="margin">Collodion of Statutes.</note> declared to be appending and belonging, and knit unto <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So was it in the Reign of King <hi>Henry</hi> the Eighth, when, by the States of the Realm, he was declared King thereof. And 11 of Queen <hi>Eliz.</hi> her Title to that King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom is recogniz'd in Parliament, and declar'd to be very Ancient, and derived from <hi>Gurmund</hi> (Son of <hi>Belin,</hi> King of <hi>Brittain</hi>) Lord of <hi>Bayon</hi> in <hi>Spain:</hi> ſome of whoſe Subjects he permitted to live in that Iſland, and ſent Guides with them to ſettle them in it; who, with their Poſterity, ought therefore to be ſubject unto <hi>England,</hi> as the Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Plantations in <hi>America</hi> now are.</p>
            <p>But though the Title of <hi>England</hi> to that Kingdom be ſo clear, ſo very ancient and juſt, yet they have openly rebell'd five times in leſs than fourſcore years, beginning in the Year 1567. Two other Rebellions were alſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triv'd and reſolved on within that ſpace, to which they had Promiſes of Foreign Aid; but were, by God's Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, diſcover'd and prevented: beſide that intended, and begun by three of their Principal Cities in the beginning of King <hi>James</hi>'s Reign. So very prone and apt they have always been to Rebel upon the Acceſſion of Princes to the Throne; or when <hi>England</hi> was engag'd in Wars, either Domeſtick or Forreign.</p>
            <p>And the like opportunity they made uſe of in the late unhappy War, violating all Laws of God, Nature, and Nations; and throwing off their Allegiance to their un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubted Soveraign, as ſoon as the Troubles began in this
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:101735:10"/>Kingdom. To which Wickedneſs their Clergy, of all ſorts, did then ſeduce them, telling them, That Faith was not to be kept with Hereticks; That the Pope, being God's Vicar, <hi>Pro-Deus,</hi> as <hi>Mart. Azpilcueta</hi> calls him, had Power to depoſe Heretical Princes; and that they would do God and the Church good Service in killing Hereticks. Upon which they ran furiouſly to commit thoſe horrid Acts which they thought meritorious. And ſo cunningly did they draw Arguments from Religion, Honour, and Profit, that they made the <hi>Engliſh Pale</hi> break out, which nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Pope's Bulls, nor the Declarations of the Divines of <hi>Salamanca</hi> and <hi>Valedolid</hi> could inſtigate them unto in the Reign of Queen <hi>Elizabeth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But now they had better digeſted the Romiſh Tenets; and the Prieſts appear'd every where in the Head of their Troops, and in ſharp and bloody Oratory animated them to go on.</p>
            <p>What the Jeſuits had wrote was become Canonical; and the Actions of others were now to be imitated. Why ſhould not they be as blindly Zealous, as any of their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion had been? They knew the <hi>Merindolians</hi> and <hi>Cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brians</hi> were murder'd for their Averſion to the Romiſh Religion: that <hi>Alphonſus Diazius</hi> came, in great Zeal from <hi>Rome,</hi> and kill'd his own Brother in <hi>Germany,</hi> for be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a Proteſtant. They had heard how many had been martyr'd here, in the Reign of Queen <hi>Mary;</hi> and what numbers the Duke <hi>de Alva</hi> had executed in the <hi>Nether<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lands.</hi> The Maſſacre of <hi>Paris</hi> was freſh in their memory; where, and in other parts of <hi>France,</hi> the French King boaſted in his Letters to the Pope, that he had cut off 70000 Hereticks; for which there were ſolemn Proceſſions at <hi>Rome,</hi> and a Jubilee granted to all Chriſtendom by the Pope; who, by Cardinal <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rſinus,</hi> gave thanks to the French King for that good Service, and deſir'd him to go
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:101735:11"/>on, and extirpate Hereſie out of his Kingdoms. They knew the many Plots and Confederacies againſt Queen <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lizabeth</hi> and King <hi>James;</hi> and how ſome of thoſe mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrous Parricides gloried in their Sin, at their Execution.</p>
            <p>And beſide theſe bloody Examples, they had the Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of their Learned Writers for the lawfulneſs of ſuch Actions.<note place="margin">De Reg. l. <hi>6.</hi> c. <hi>6.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Mariana</hi> had told them, <hi>That if the Prince wont be advis'd, they may take up Arms againſt him; and if nothing elſe will do, they may kill him.</hi> And <hi>Emanuel Sa</hi> had ſaid, <hi>When once he is Excommunicated, the People, who have ſworn Allegiance to him, may depoſe him; and any one may be his Executioner.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lib. <hi>6.</hi> c. <hi>3.</hi> &amp; <hi>6.</hi>
               </note> And <hi>Suarez</hi> had encourag'd them to it likewiſe; telling them, <hi>If Subjects were once abſolv'd from their Oaths, they might riſe up againſt their Natural Prince, and kill him.</hi> And their great Cardinal <hi>Bellarmin</hi> left them alſo many rebellious Inſtructions,<note place="margin">De Cler. lib. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>29.</hi>
               </note> too tedious to relate; and ſaid, <hi>That all agree, that if the King be Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rannical, or Heretical, he may, and ought to de deprived of his Kingdom:</hi> Nay, he adds, to prevent an Objection, <hi>Si hoc minus factum ſit priſcis temporibus, cauſa est, quia de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erant vires:</hi>
               <note place="margin">De Pont. l. <hi>3.</hi> c. <hi>7.</hi>
               </note> though he could not but know that <hi>Tertullian</hi> and St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> tell us the quite contrary.</p>
            <p>But theſe Modern Authors having ſaid otherwiſe, their Authority did ſoon prevail; and having both Precedents and Commands for ſuch horrid Acts, they took up Arms, and committed the moſt execrable Villanies that ever any Mortal read, or heard of: Some of their chief Prelates and greateſt Clergy-men being their Officers and Commanders; and others writing and preaching in defence of their Wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs. I might name many; but ſhall only tell you, that their Biſhop of <hi>Ferns</hi> calls it <hi>a juſt War;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Bleeding</hi> Iphigenia.</note> and ſays, <hi>They were forced to take Arms to avoid their own Destruction, and in the neceſſary Defence of their Estates and Religion.</hi> And how much he, and the reſt of their Biſhops, oppoſed
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:101735:11"/>the Ceſſation, is notoriouſly known: and did not Father <hi>Molief</hi> cauſe them (contrary to the Law of Arms) to tear the Heralds Coat, who proclaim'd the Peace at <hi>Lymerick;</hi> for which he had Thanks from the <hi>Nuncio,</hi> and the Apoſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Benediction? And were not all Excommunicated who adhered to that Peace? I could trace them from place to place, and ſhew you how vigorous and active they were in all parts of the Kingdom: But I haſten.</p>
            <p>You ſee, by their Books and Practices, they hold it lawful to extirpate Proteſtant Kings and their Subjects: and, while they retain ſuch Principles, what Safety can we expect? What Proteſtant Prince and Country is not in danger? What may they not fear, when the Fathers of their Church, who ſhould reſtrain them from ſuch horrid Murthers, do, by Precept and Example, prompt them un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them, and juſtifie them by Religious Arguments?</p>
            <p>And if their People may be abſolv'd from their Oaths of Allegiance, as the Duke of <hi>Suevia</hi> was by <hi>Gregory</hi> the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth from his Oath to the Emperour <hi>Henry</hi> the Fourth, and the Engliſh, by Pope <hi>Pius,</hi> in the Reign of Queen <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lizabeth,</hi> how can Princes be ſecure? And while they allow of Equivocating and Mental Reſervations in taking of Oaths, to what purpoſe are they adminiſtred? And while they hold that the Commands of their Superiours muſt be obſerv'd, as the Command and Will of God, there is lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle likelyhood of Peace hereafter: Nor need we wonder at former Conſpiracies, the Clergy having ſuch power o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver their Conſciences, and holding ſuch Principles, and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proving of ſuch Actions; on both which I might abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly enlarge. But having ſhew'd you how this Rebellion began, upon what Principles, and at whoſe Inſtigation, what could follow, but the greateſt Cruelty that could be committed? Of which you expect ſome Relation and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Inſtances alſo this Day.</p>
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:101735:12"/>
            <p> But alas! what Heart can think of it; what Tongue can expreſs it without great Emotion and Concern? The very remembrance of it ſtrikes Dread and Terrour into my Soul. For being thus inſtructed, and enraged by the Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuits, Prieſts, and Fryars, (as the Act of Parliament for the Obſervation of this Day tells you,) they began a moſt cruel, bloody, and unnatural Rebellion, reſolving to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy both Church and State, and cut off all the Proteſtants that would not joyn with them in their Superſtitious and Idolatrous Worſhip. To effect which, they roſe this day in all Parts of the Nation, running, like Furies, up and down, breathing forth nothing but Death, and finding no delight but in Slaughter; their Hands reeking with Blood, and their Swords and Skeins dull'd and rebated with hew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Chriſtians in pieces; their Zeal hurrying them into the greateſt Violations of Religion and Humanity that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the Sun beheld.</p>
            <p>They fully verified this Text in the greatneſs of their Rage, and ſpared but few whom they could kill. Grey hairs were no protection to the Aged; neither could Beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty or Youth find any Mercy from them; and even Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency it ſelf could not ſave the ſucking Infants from being toſſed on their Pikes, and hung on Tenterhooks. It was Crime enough in thoſe poor Souls to be born of Proteſtant Parents. Some tender Virgins fled in Froſt and Snow to the Woods and Deſerts; and when ſharp Hunger drove them out of thoſe doleful Solitudes, they were catch'd, and made a Prey to their Beſtial Deſires; their Shrieks and Tears could no way move them to pity; and when by force they had ſatisfied their Luſt, they murder'd the very Perſons they had embrac'd.</p>
            <p>Hanging and drowning were Acts of Mercy among them; for they kill'd Men by degrees, as the Tyrant <hi>Caligu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la</hi> did,<note place="margin">In the Caſtle of <hi>Moroghan.</hi>
               </note> that they might feel themſelves dye, tying one naked
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:101735:12"/>to a Table, and giving him a Gaſh at every Health they drank, until his whole Body was one continued wound. Nor were their Women leſs cruel to their own Sex,<note place="margin">Bp. <hi>Maxwel</hi>'s Examination.</note> bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barouſly killing the Proteſtant Women; and even their Children (as if they had ſuck'd in ferity with their Milk) murdring the Proteſtants Children.<note place="margin">Examination of <hi>Adam Clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver.</hi>
               </note> And a Youth, not above fourteen years of Age, ſlew fifteen men, being diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arm'd, and in the Stocks: and another, about twelve, kill'd two Women and one Man at the Siege of <hi>Agher.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>They brake the Back-bone of a young man,<note place="margin">Bp. <hi>Maxwel</hi>'s Examination.</note> and would not kill him, but remov'd him from place to place, to eat the Graſs of the Field; and roaſted Mr. <hi>Watſon</hi> alive, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter they had cut off ſome pieces of his fleſh.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exam. of</hi> Phil. Taylor <hi>and</hi> John Wiſdom.</note> They rip't up the Bellies of Women, and caſt their Children to the Swine, who eat them; and ſome were delivered of Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren while they were hanging. They made a man drunk,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exam. of</hi> Alex. Creighton, Ch. Campbell, <hi>and</hi> Geo Cotting<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham <hi>Clerk.</hi>
               </note> and then hang'd him. They forc'd others to Maſs, gave them the Sacrament, and then murder'd them; ſaying, <hi>It was no ſin to kill Proteſtants, for they were all damn'd al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nay,<note place="margin">Bp. <hi>Maxwel</hi>'s Examination.</note> their Cruelty did extend to the very Cattel of the Engliſh, cutting pieces out of them alive; in which Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment they liv'd ſome days, roaring about the Fields.</p>
            <p>They compell'd ſome to tread on the Holy Bible, cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing it in a horrid manner, and ſaying,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exam. of</hi> Ed. Slack, Rog. Holland, <hi>and Mr.</hi> Dean.</note> 
               <hi>It had bred all the quarrel.</hi> They alſo burnt ſome Bibles, and ſaid, <hi>It was Hell-fire that burnt; and wiſh'd they had all the Bibles in Chriſtendom to burn with them.</hi> And they triumph'd and rejoyc'd in the numbers they had kill'd, ſaying,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exam. of</hi> John Wiſdom, Phil. Taylor, <hi>and</hi> Marg. Stoakes.</note> 
               <hi>The Devil was beholding to them for ſending him ſo many Souls to Hell.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But their Rage againſt the Clergy was ſuch,<note place="margin">Mr <hi>Harcourt</hi>'s Martyrology.</note> as I am not able to relate, nor could you, without Horrour and Amazement, hear it. And the barbarous uſage of one of
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:101735:13"/>their Wives is not to be nam'd among Chriſtians.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mrs.</hi> Smithſon.</note> They drown'd and burnt great numbers, and laugh'd at their Cries and Lamentations; and took pleaſure to hear Men ſpeak, as they buried them alive in Ditches.<note place="margin">Exam. of <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tho. Stratford.</hi> Abſtract of Iriſh Maſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cres.</note> They tried whether a Man's Guts or a Dogs were longeſt; and made Candles of a Man's greaſe in the County of <hi>Tyrone,</hi> and did many other things which Nature loaths, and Huma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity abhors: as may be at large ſeen in the Examinations taken upon Oath,<note place="margin">Bp. of <hi>Meath.</hi>
               </note> by a late eminent and learned Prelate, with ſeven other Reverend Divines,<note place="margin">Dr. <hi>Jones'</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrance. Mr. <hi>Harcourt</hi>'s Remonſtrance Sir <hi>John Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple</hi>'s Hiſt. Dr. <hi>Borlaſes</hi> Hiſt.</note> and in other Books writ on this Tragical Subject, to which I refer you: and in them you will ſee, that <hi>Piſo</hi>'s Head never afforded more pleaſure to the inhumane <hi>Otho,</hi> than the dead Carkaſſes of Proteſtants did to thoſe men. A quick death was the on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly favour, and the greateſt Act of Humanity to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected at their Hands: but alas! even that was ſometimes deny'd, though moſt earneſtly deſired by thoſe whom they had grievouſly wounded.</p>
            <p>The whole Kingdom was an Aceldema, and nothing but Sighs and Groans were heard throughout the Land. When <hi>Titus</hi> ſaw <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> in flames, and <hi>Marcellus</hi> beheld <hi>Syracuſa</hi> burning, their Words and Tears did teſtifie their trouble and concern, though Enemies, for the deſtruction of thoſe Noble Places; but theſe men ſung, with <hi>Nero,</hi> while they burnt our Cities, demoliſhed our Churches, and buried thoſe Sacred Fabricks in their own Ruins, becauſe they had been us'd by Hereticks.</p>
            <p>All the Country was in a flame. The Towns were fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with the Blood of the Inhabitants; and the Bodies left in many places to be devoured by the Fowls of the Air. Nay,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exam. of</hi> Mar. Woods, Tho. Hewetſon, <hi>and</hi> Rob. Collis.</note> they violated the very Sepulchres of the Dead, dug up their Bodies, and threw them into the Sea, or into the Fields, as unworthy to be interr'd among them.</p>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:101735:13"/>
            <p> Naturaliſts tell us, the fierceſt Lions covet Honour more than Revenge; they are appeas'd when they ſee their E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy on the Ground, and give Life to that which yields the Victory: but that could not ſatisfie theſe Men. To ſee the Brittiſh poor and miſerable, was not enough; 'twas their Blood alone could quench the thirſt of ſuch Canibals. I might give you numerous Examples of their Rage and Fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, but I ſhall end, the whole Day being little enough to give you a full account of their Villanies, which were ſo great and ſavage, ſo barbarous and inhumane, that no E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pithet can reach them, no Hiſtory can parallel them. For proof of which, you have the undeniable Teſtimony of the whole Parliament of <hi>Ireland,</hi> who, with one Voice, tell you in their <hi>Act</hi> for the keeping this Anniverſary, That it <hi>was a Conſpiracy ſo generally inhumane, barbarous, and cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el, as the like before was never heard off in any Age or King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Which <hi>Act,</hi> we need not wonder they would <hi>Repeal,</hi> it being the united Evidence of thoſe, who were met in Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, from all parts of the Nation, and had fully en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired into their Actions, and had alſo many among them who had been Eye-witneſſes of their Cruelties; to ſmother which; the Iriſh had uſed all the Art and Induſtry imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble: and to terrifie all from any farther ſearch into them, did moſt barbarouſly murther Arch-deacon <hi>Byſſe,</hi> who was appointed by Authority to take Examinations of their Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pines and Murders; which, in a word, were ſo many, and ſo ſpitefully acted, that the moſt compendious Writer could ſcarce comprize them in a Volume, and the ſharpeſt Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyriſt repreſent them in their juſt Characters.</p>
            <p>Such was their Rage; thus exceſſive and immoderate was their Fury, that we may ſay of it,<note place="margin">Gen. 49.6, 7.</note> as <hi>Jacob</hi> did of the Rage of his Sons, <hi>O my Soul, come not thou into their ſecret, unto their aſſembly, mine Honour, be not thou united; for in
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:101735:14"/>their Anger they ſlew a man. Curſed be their Anger, for it was fierce, and their Wrath, for it was cruel. I will divide them in</hi> Jacob, <hi>and ſcatter them in</hi> Iſrael. By which pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thetical Apoſtrophe, he ſhews his great and zealous deteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of their Outrage, curſes their ſin, and foretells their puniſhment: which was accordingly fulfilled, when their Union in Evil was puniſh'd with a Diviſion and Scattering among the Ten Tribes.</p>
            <p>Neither did theſe bloody men long eſcape, Vengeance did purſue them cloſe at the Heels. None values the Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutioner when the work is done. <hi>Alexander</hi> was rais'd to puniſh the Pride of the <hi>Perſians;</hi> and <hi>Caeſar</hi> and <hi>Pompey</hi> the Luſt and Luxury of the <hi>Romans:</hi> But when God had done his work with them, they came to ſudden and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timely ends. And ſo did our juſt God deal with the mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cileſs <hi>Iriſh;</hi> for beſide vaſt numbers which were ſlain in the War, great Plagues and ſharp Famines came among them, ſo very great, that they did eat one another in ſome pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. The Wrath of God fell heavy upon them, as it did on the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> and they were moſt grievouſly puniſh'd for the Blood which they had ſpilt.</p>
            <p>Which might well have terrified them from commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the like wickedneſs any more: but alas! ſo invete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate were they againſt us, that there is no expectation of Peace among them longer than they are kept under. Their Religion alters their very Morals, ſours their Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and imbitters their Spirits: And all the Favours and kindneſs we can ſhew them, prove ineffectual. For was not the laſt Rebellion begun when they enjoy'd their Eſtates, and had the free Exerciſe of their Religion? When they were Members of Parliament, and Magiſtrates of Corporations? When their Lawyers (who were then, and are now the contrivers of our Ruin) did Practice in our Courts? And when they had all the other Priviledges
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:101735:14"/>they could reaſonably deſire? And now the whole Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of the Nation, and both Civil and Military Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployments could not ſatisfie them. They have a Natural Averſion and Antipathy to us: And have reſolv'd (as the Jeſuit <hi>Campian</hi> declar'd here) to be our Enemies for ever. And I fear they think themſelves oblig'd (as <hi>O Mahon,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Diſput. Apolog.</note> another of that Order, ſays they are) to joyn unani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouſly in the extirpation of Hereticks: and then un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly, when they have the Power in their hands, we muſt expect all the Miſchief they can do us.</p>
            <p>Of which we have lately had another fatal Inſtance; the whole Nation riſing again in Arms, ſeizing our Houſes, plundring us of our Goods, and driving us into Exile and Baniſhment, when we had liv'd Peaceably, Hoſpitably, and moſt Obligingly among them. But God in Judgment re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred Mercy; he delivered us from their Rage, he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved us in our ſudden Flight, and when no Ships could be had, he brought ſome of us in <hi>Open Boats</hi> to this Charita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and Compaſſionate Nation; where we have been kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly receiv'd, and many thouſands have been Charitably re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved; which with all gratitude and thankfulneſs muſt be for ever remembred.</p>
            <p>And God has rais'd us up a <hi>Glorious Deliverer,</hi> who has expos'd himſelf to as great dangers as ever any Prince did, to reſtore us to our Country again. He ſucceeds his Illuſtrious Anceſtors in their Hereditary Zeal for the <hi>Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Religion,</hi> as he does in their Valour; and reſcues us from Popiſh Tyranny and Slavery, as they did the <hi>Nether<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lands</hi> in the laſt Century. And by his Wiſdom, Conduct, and Courage, he has obtain'd a Victory which is the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miration of this, and will be the Wonder of future Ages: By which, the <hi>Metropolis</hi> of our Nation, and many other great Towns are preſerv'd from Flames; and the Lives of many Thouſands of Proteſtants are ſaved, and the whole
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:101735:15"/>Kingdom in a happy way of being reduc'd; and we, who were forc'd to fly, have now a joyful Proſpect of return<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing home.</p>
            <p>For which, let us pay him all Duty and Honour, all Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delity and Allegiance. Let him be as dear to us, as <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> was to the <hi>Iſraelites;</hi> and as <hi>Titus</hi> and <hi>Conſtantine</hi> were to the <hi>Romans.</hi> Let us love him as the Father of our Country, and the Defender of our Faith. Let us pray that his Arm may be ſtrong, and his Sword Victorious: And may the God of Battels Crown him with Succeſs in all his Engagements for the Proteſtant Religion.</p>
            <p>And let us this day praiſe and adore our God for that, and all other Bleſſings and Deliverances. <hi>O magnifie the Lord with me, and let us exalt his Name together; for his anger endureth but a moment. He hath turned our mourn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing into dancing, and girded us with gladneſs. They are brought down, and fallen; but we are riſen, and ſtand up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right. Let our mouth ſpeak the praiſes of the Lord, and let all fleſh bleſs his Holy Name for ever and ever.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now let his Mercies, and his Judgments have their due Influence upon us. Let us not defeat their gracious Deſign and Intention; but let us grow better under our Sufferings, and return with Reſolutions of entire Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and univerſal Amendment. Let us humble our ſelves, and bewail thoſe ſins which brought theſe Puniſhments up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on us; and <hi>ſin no more, leſt a worſe thing come unto us.</hi> And while we live, let us bleſs the Lord, who has delivered us from our mercileſs Enemies. Let us live up to the Mercies we have received, and walk anſwerable to the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours he hath beſtowed upon us and our Fore-fathers, in diſcovering the Plots and Contrivances of our Adverſaries, and preſerving us on this day from their intended Cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties.</p>
            <pb n="27" facs="tcp:101735:15"/>
            <p> We may well conclude by their murdering ſo many, they would have done the like to all, had not God detected their Deſigns, reſtrained their Malice, and made a way for us to eſcape. He did not quite caſt off his People, nor forſake his Inheritance: But was, as <hi>David</hi> calls him, <hi>a preſent help in the time of trouble.</hi> For when we were ſurrounded with bloody Men, when the Snare was laid, and the Pit was dug, and we were juſt falling into them, he pull'd us back, and reſcu'd us from them, as he did the Jews from <hi>Haman</hi>'s Conſpiracy. For which, this our Feaſt of <hi>Purim</hi> is to be kept with all Thankfulneſs and Devotion. <hi>For now may our</hi> Iſrael <hi>ſay, If the Lord had not been on our ſide when men roſe up againſt us, they had ſwallowed us up quick, when their wrath was kindled againſt us:</hi> Or, in the words of my Text, <hi>They had ſlain us with a rage that would have reached up to Heaven.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Bleſſed be the Lord, who hath not given us as a Prey unto their Teeth. <hi>Our Soul is eſcaped, as a Bird out of the Snare of the Fowler;</hi> and we are yet living Monuments of his Mercy. And let us conclude, in the words of the Collect: <hi>It was his Goodneſs, not our Merit; it was his Mercy, not our Foreſight, that any were left alive when they roſe up againſt us.</hi> To him therefore, on this day of Mercy, and all the days of our Life, and in all Generations to come, be aſcribed, as is moſt due, all Honour and Glory, for ever and ever. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:101735:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>BOOKS Printed for, and are to be ſold by <hi>Robert Clavel</hi> at the <hi>Peacock</hi> in St. <hi>Paul's Church-yard.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>A Sermon preached before the Court of Aldermen and Citizens of <hi>London,</hi> at <hi>Guild-hall Chappel,</hi> on <hi>Sunday September</hi> the 16. 1688.</p>
            <p>The Golden Rule, or Royal Law of Equity Explain'd. Both by <hi>J. Goodman,</hi> D.D.</p>
            <p>An Account of the Tranſactions of the late K. <hi>James</hi> in <hi>Ireland,</hi> wherein is contained the Act of Attainder paſt at <hi>Dublin</hi> in <hi>May</hi> 1689. As alſo the Proclamation for Raiſing Twenty thouſand pounds <hi>per Menſem,</hi> without an Act of Parliament, with other Proclamations and Acts made there.</p>
            <p>A Liſt of ſuch of the Names of the Nobility, Gentry, and Commonalty of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Ireland</hi> (amongſt whom are ſeveral Women and Children) who are all by an Act of a pretended Parliament aſſembled in <hi>Dublin</hi> on the 7th of <hi>May</hi> 1689. before the late K. <hi>James,</hi> Attainted of High Treaſon. Both Licenſed by the Command of his Majeſties Principal Secretary of State.</p>
            <p>Seaſonable Reflections on a late Pamphlet, Entituled, A Hiſtory of Paſſive Obedience ſince the Reformation, where the true Notion of Paſſive Obedience is ſettled and ſecured from the malicious Interpretations of deſigning Men.</p>
            <p>Obedience and Submiſſion to the preſent Government, demonſtrated from Biſhop <hi>Overal</hi>'s Convocation Book.</p>
            <p>A Letter of Advice to a young Gentleman of an Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable Family, now in his Travels beyond Seas, for his more ſafe and profitable Conduct in the Three great Inſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of Study, Moral Deportment, and Religion.</p>
            <p>The Life of the Right Reverend Father in God <hi>Ed. Rainbow,</hi> D. D. late Lord Biſhop of <hi>Carliſle.</hi> To which is added a Sermon preached at his Funeral by Mr. <hi>Tho. Tully</hi> his Lordſhips Chaplain, and Chancellour of the ſaid Dioceſs of <hi>Carliſle,</hi> at <hi>Dalſtone, April</hi> the 1ſt, 1690.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:101735:16"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
